Finding Aid for Charles Tyley Newton Papers, 1907-1947
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Tyley Newton Papers 1907-1947
Newton, Charles Tyley, 1893-
4 linear feet
852014 Aa 2
Ypsilanti, Michigan automobile salesman, antique collector for Greenfield Village, and real estate agent for the Ford Motor Company. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and pamphlet material concerning his work for Ford Motor Company, and his interest in William H. McGuffey and Stephen Foster; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Roscoe O. Bonisteel (donor no. 2035 ). The provenance of the material is uncertain.
The collection is open to research.
Charles Newton worked for Henry Ford in the Secretary's Office in the 1920s and 1930s. His principal responsibility was in the acquisition of items for Greenfield Village and the Henry Ford Museum.
The collection has been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Newspaper clippings; Printed Material; Greenfield Village acquisitions; Real estate acquisitions; and Photographs.
Subjects:
Automobile industry and trade--United States.; Ford Motor Company.; Foster, Stephen Collins, 1826-1864.; Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village.; McGuffey, William Holmes, 1800-1873.; Newton, Charles Tyley, 1893-; Willow Run Bomber Plant.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Abandoned buildings.; African American women--Work.; Agricultural machinery.; Airplanes--1908.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Farms.; Ann Arbor Club.; Architecture.; Arnold Lake (Clare County, Mich.); Au Sable River (Mich.); Automobile industry.; Automobile service stations--Michigan--Marshall.; Automobile service stations--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Automobiles.; Baptist Parsonage (Saline, Mich.); Baraga Lumber Company.; Barbershops.; Barns.; Beaches.; Bedrooms.; Bicycles and tricycles--1861-1870.; Boats.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Calumet (Mich.); Carriages and coaches.; Carts and wagons.; City and town halls--Michigan--Marshall.; Clarkston (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Clothing and dress--1861-1870.; Clothing and dress--1891-1900.; Clothing and dress--1901-1910.; Clothing and dress--1921-1930.; Comins (Mich.); Covered bridges.; Dams.; Dance.; Deward (Mich.); Dundee (Mich.)--Mills.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dwellings--Michigan--Clarkston.; Dwellings--Michigan--Gilbert Lake.; Dwellings--Michigan--Saline.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Estates.; Families.; Farms.; Farms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Farms--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Fireplaces.; Fishing--Michigan.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Ford Motor Company.; Gilbert Lake (Oakland County, Mich.)--Dwellings.; Glennie (Mich.); Henry Ford Museum and Greenfield Village.; Horses.; Hotels and taverns--Michigan--Ypsilanti.; Hunting--United States.; Industrial buildings.; Interiors.; Irish Hills (Mich.); Kalkaska County (Mich.); Kitchens--1941-1950.; Kneeland-Bigelow Company.; Laborers.; L'Anse (Mich.); Living rooms.; Livingston County (Mich.); Log cabins.; H.M. Loud and Sons Lumber Company (Oscoda, Mich.); Lucking Farm (Ypsilanti, Mich.); Lumber industry.; Manchester (Mich.); Marshall (Mich.)--Automobile service stations.; Marshall (Mich.)--City and town halls.; Metamora (Mich.); Mills--Michigan--Dundee.; Music ensembles.; Nash Distributing Company.; Newkirk, Birkett.; Newkirk family.; Newton, Charles Tyley, 1893-; Newton family.; Oakland County (Mich.); Oscoda (Mich.); Pine River (Mich.: River); Porter-Hicks Farm (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Privies.; Railroad stations.; Railroads--Michigan.; Raisin River (Mich.); Saline (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ships--Great Lakes.; Sleds and sleighs.; Slums.; South Branch (Mich.); Stagecoaches.; Steam engines.; Street-railroads--Michigan.; Trucks.; Ward, David, 1822-1900.; Willow Run (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Women.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Business enterprises.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Farms.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Hotels and taverns.
Genre Terms:
Tintypes.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated 1907-1947, 16 folders (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - Willow Run Bomber Plant 1941-1943, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1945-1947 (Box 1)
- Printed Material
  - Automobile industry, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ford Motor Company, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Boat construction 1908-1911 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1912-1944 (Box 1)
- Greenfield Village acquisitions circa 1928-1946
  - William Holmes McGuffey material 1934-1940, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Stephen Foster birthplace 1935-1939 (Box 2)
  - Abraham Lincoln items, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Regarding song "When you and I were young Maggie", 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Early automobile items (Box 2)
  - Covered bridges (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 2)
- Real estate acquisitions
  - Purchase of real estate by the Ford Motor Company circa 1930-1946 (Box 3)
    (unprocessed)
- Photographs
  - Portraits, snapshots, and photos of friends and family members, include tintypes (Box 4)
    (include photo of Newton with Henry Ford)
  - Subjects
    - Agricultural Machinery (Box 4)
    - Airplanes, includes Ford Motor Airplane 1908 (Box 4)
    - Ann Arbor Club (Box 4)
    - Automobiles
      - General (Box 4)
      - Nash Distributing Company (includes trucks) (Box 4)
    - Barbershop and barber chairs (Box 4)
    - Barns and other farm buildings (Box 4)
    - Bicycles (Box 4)
    - Bridges, Covered (Box 4)
    - Carriages
      - Coaches (Box 4)
      - Horse and buggy (Box 4)
      - Sleighs (Box 4)
      - Wagons (Box 4)
    - Clothing and dress (Box 4)
    - Dancing (Box 4)
    - Drain Tile plant (unidentified) (Box 4)
    - Dry goods store (unidentified), tintype (Box 4)
    - Fishing (include boats) (Box 4)
    - Horses (Box 4)
    - Hotel (United States Hotel) (Box 4)
    - Houses
      - General unidentified, 7 envelopes (Box 4)
      - Faulkrod Home (Box 4)
        (include interiors)
      - Haynes Home (Box 4)
    - Hunting (Box 4)
    - Industrial plants and machinery (and shop interiors) (Box 4)
    - Lumbering (by place or company name)
      - Au Sable River (Box 4)
      - Baraga Lumber Company (Box 4)
      - Comins (Brook's camp) (Box 4)
      - Comins (Fitzpatrick's camp) (Box 4)
      - Comins (Joe Lalonde's camp) (Box 4)
      - Comins (unidentified) (Box 4)
      - DeWald (mill) (Box 4)
      - Glennie (J.H. Hayes' camp) (Box 4)
      - Kalkaska County (David Ward camps) (Box 4)
      - Kneeland-Bigelow Company (Box 4)
      - L'Anse (lumber camp) (Box 4)
      - Oscoda (Loud and Son Lumber Company) (Box 4)
      - Oscoda (unidentified) (Box 4)
      - Pine River (T.T. Allen's Lumber camps) (Box 4)
      - Pine River (unidentified) (Box 4)
      - Smith Lumbering Camp (Box 4)
      - South Branch (Gates camp and unidentified) (Box 4)
    - Lumbering (by activity)
      - Booms; river views (Box 4)
      - Lumbermen; camp scenes (Box 4)
      - Mills (general) (Box 4)
      - Mills (Box 4)
        (include photos of inspection by Henry Ford)
      - Miscellaneous activities (Box 4)
      - Railroads (Box 4)
      - Transport (Box 4)
      - Stacked lumber (Box 4)
      - Ships and dock scenes (Box 4)
    - Musicians (Box 4)
    - Outhouses (Box 4)
    - Railroads (Box 4)
      (includes Ypsilanti photograph see also Lumber--Railroads)
    - Railroads) (Box 4)
    - Ships (Box 4)
    - Street railroads (Box 4)
    - Tractors and other steam machinery (Box 4)
    - Waterworks; dams (Box 4)
  - Geographical Subjects
    - Ann Arbor area (Box 4)
    - Bloomfield Township, Gilbert Lake (home) (Box 4)
    - Calumet (Box 4)
    - Canada (Mansion on Detroit River) (Box 4)
    - Cherry Hill (Huston Farm) (Box 4)
    - Clarkston
      - General (Box 4)
      - Russell Street Home (Box 4)
    - Dearborn: Greenfield Village
      - McGuffy School House and related (Box 4)
      - Stephen Foster House (Box 4)
      - Washington's Mill (Pa.) (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Dundee (Box 4)
      (Raisin River, mill, dam, waterworks)
    - Harrison, Arnold Lake (Box 4)
    - Irish Hills (Morgan Farm) (Box 4)
    - Livingston County, Pinckney district, Hill Creek Farm (Box 4)
    - Manchester (landscape of surrounding area) (Box 4)
    - Marshall (Box 4)
      (automobile service station; other buildings)
    - Metamora, Lapeer County (Box 4)
    - Oakland County, Springfield Township (Ford-Bryant Lane) (Box 4)
    - Saline (Baptist parsonage) (Box 4)
    - Willow Run (condemned houses) (Box 4)
    - Ypsilanti
      - General (Box 4)
      - Power lines and road maintenance near Ypsilanti (Box 4)
  - People
    - Birkett Newkirk family (Box 4)
      (includes portraits of children and women)
    - Ford, Edsel (Box 4)
    - McGuffy, William H., family (Box 4)
    - Wilton Harry and Elizabeth (Box 4)